A Guide to the Rockefeller Foundation records, Audiovisual materials FA752
Rockefeller Archive Center
Rockefeller Foundation records, Audiovisual materials
1922-1999
Rockefeller Archive Center
Rockefeller Foundation
FA752
45 film reels Actual extent unknown
Conditions Governing Access
When requesting to view audiovisual material, please refer to the Title and the AV Number (example: AV 1916). Researchers are asked to check the "Restrictions" note for each Title. If a Title does not currently have an access copy, please contact a RAC archivist for further instruction. All inquiries to view films require advanced notice of at least 2 business days, and may necessitate notice of up to one week. Individual items, including those that are not available in modern formats, may be restricted from access at the discretion of RAC.
Rockefeller Foundation
- Rockefeller Foundation Films, 1
  Arrangement
  Alphabetical.
  Scope and Contents
  Types of records include: films.
  Conditions Governing Access
  When requesting to view audiovisual material, please refer to the Title and the AV Number (example: AV 1916). Researchers are asked to check the "Restrictions" note for each Title. If a Title does not currently have an access copy, please contact a RAC archivist for further instruction.
  All inquiries to view films require advanced notice of at least 2 business days, and may necessitate notice of up to one week. Individual items, including those that are not available in modern formats, may be restricted from access at the discretion of RAC.
  - Adventure in Sardinia, 1950; Sound, Black & white, 20 minutes.; 16mm film (Reel AV 126)
    Conditions Governing Access note
    Access copy currently unavailable. Please contact a RAC archivist for further instruction.
    Scope and Contents note
    The second half of a film about the ERLAAS project in Sardinia (The first half is "The Sardinian Project"). Describes the land and people of Sardinia before the malaria eradication program - difficulties of life in villages, land defoliated, rampant disease, and so on. Introduces the ERLAAS staff, under the direction of Dr. John Loyan, and their efforts to combat the disease using DDT spray over 10,000 square miles. Produced by British Pathe Production for the Economic Cooperation Administration.
  - Botanical Expedition to the Heart of the Aegilops, 1963; Sound, Color, 9 minutes.; 16mm film (Reel AV 125)
    Access copy currently unavailable. Please contact an RAC archivist for further instruction.
    The search for perfected strains of wheat in Greece, Lebanon, Turkey, and Egypt. Footage from Ankar University laboratories with agricultural research.
  - Buscando Una Agricultura Mejor, 1958; Sound, Color, 28 minutes.; 16mm film (Reel AV 28)
    Film of the Cotaxtla Experimental Station in Mexico, researching food sources such as bananas, mangoes, and pineapples. Irrigation, weeding, cross-breeding, lab work, and inspection of variant plant strands. Construction of farm buildings and specialized machinery. Farmers from across Mexico coming to Cotaxtla for training and modernization.
  - La Ciencia Agricola Impulsa Al Noroeste, 1960s; Sound, Color, 22 minutes.; 16mm film (Reel AV 29)
    Ffilm about agricultural sciences in Mexico; new research and technologies encouraging cross-breeding, pesticides, irrigation, etc.
  - Comentarios Sobre Asistencia Technica Cooperativa Por Su Excelencia Don Julian Rodriguez Adame, Secretario de Agricultura Y Ganadera, Republica de Mexico, 1961; Sound, Black & white, 6 minutes.; 16mm film (Reel AV 121)
    Unedited film trims from 1961 film of His Excellency Don Julian Rodrigues-Adame, Secretary of Agriculture and Livestock, Republic of Mexico, commenting on cooperative RF/Mexican farm research projects. Part of the film Harvest.
  - Composers Performers Workshop, 1965; Silent, Black & white, 9 minutes.; 16mm film (Reel AV 113)
    Conference at the North Texas State University in Dallas, Texas (funded by a Rockefeller Foundation grant).
  - La Cria de Pollitos, 1961; Sound, Color, 14 minutes.; 16mm film (Reel AV 129)
    General note
    Spanish
    Film of scientific methods in Mexico for breeding chickens. Shows incubators, cross-breeding, sanitation methods, warming environments, etc.
  - Dorothy Gordon Youth Forum: The Well-Being of Mankind, Part I, 1963 March 31; Sound, Color, 31 minutes.; 16mm film (Reel AV 47)
    Interview with J.G. Harrar, Ralph Bunche, and several international Rockefeller Foundation Fellows in connection with the RF 50th anniversary, and the publication of "The Well-Being of Mankind". Questions posed: Is the RF work aiding mankind? Is the training applicable to the real world? What are the most acute needs in certain countries? What is the United Nations doing to help poverty-sticken populations?
  - Dorothy Gordon Youth Forum: The Well-Being of Mankind, Part II, 1963 April 7; Sound, Color, 31 minutes.; 16mm film (Reel AV 48)
    Continuation of interview with J.G Harrar, Ralph Bunche, and several international Rockefeller Foundation Fellows in connection with the RF 50th anniversary, and the publication of "The Well-Being of Mankind". Questions: What is the role of the private foundation? How do you feel about the recently-inaugurated Peace Corps? Are the RF and other organizations making real change in the US?
  - Dr. Eisenhower Vista Cotaxtla, 1960; Silent, Black & white, 8 minutes.; 16mm film (Reel AV 119)
    Dr. Milton Eisenhower visits with RF staff at the Cotaxtla labs.
  - Los Expertos Contestan (The Experts Answer), 1963; Sound, Color, 60 minutes.; 16mm film (Reel AV 44)
    Panel interviews J.G. Harrar. Film of television program in cooperation with the University of Maryland. Produced by the U.S. Information Service.
    Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
    Film contains two lengthy sections where image goes to black. Commerical advertisements would have been insterted at these spots.
  - Feeding the Billions: Tomorrow's World, 1968; Sound, Color, 60 minutes.; 16mm film (Reel AV 148)
    Film about food sources for the future: population developments and how agriculture and the environment will have to adapt to keep up with the need. IRRI work and other scientific solutions.
  - Forrage Ensilado, 1960; Sound, Color, 15 minutes.; 16mm film (Reel AV 132)
    Mexican efforts to improve dairy practices: forage crops, enriched milk via experimental strains of grass, and restoring depleted lands.
  - Harvest, 1961; Sound, Color, 33 minutes; 16mm film (Reel AV 861)
    Access copy available.
    Film showing agricultural experiments in Mexico, Chile, Argentina, and Columbia, but focuses on production and research in Mexico. Footage of E.J. Welhausen discussing RF experimental work, lab experiments, cross-breeding, etc. The RAC also has the unedited original footage from this production.
  - Harvest - Work Print Reel #1: Edwin J. Wellhausen at Telpatzingo, 1961; 16mm film (Reel AV 845)
  - Harvest - Work Print Reel #2: Agraria Seed Processing Plant, Palmira R2, 1961; 16mm film (Reel AV 846)
  - Harvest - Work Print Reel #3: (Corn) Tepalzingo, 1961; 16mm film (Reel AV 847)
  - Harvest - Work Print Reel #4: Refrigerating machinery, 1961; 16mm film (Reel AV 848)
  - Harvest - Work Print Reel #5: (Corn) Corn Festival, 1961; 16mm film; Silent, color, 13 minutes (Reel AV 849)
  - Harvest - Work Print Reel #6: (Wheat) CIANO, 1961; 16mm film (Reel AV 850)
  - Harvest - Work Print Reel #7: (Wheat) Norman Borlaug Walks, 1961; 16mm film (Reel AV 851)
  - Harvest - Work Print Reel #8: (Corn in art) National School of Agriculture, Mexico, 1961; 16mm film (Reel AV 852)
  - Harvest - Work Print Reel #9: Countryside and Rural and Urban Slums, 1961; 16mm film (Reel AV 853)
  - Harvest - Work Print Reel #10: National University and City Scenes, 1961; 16mm film (Reel AV 854)
  - Harvest - Workprint Reel #11: Mexico/Columbia Interviews, 1961; 16mm film (Reel AV 855)
  - Harvest - Workprint Reel #12: Mexico Field Day, Cotaxtla Experiment Station, 1961; 16mm film (Reel AV 856)
  - Harvest - Workprint Reel #13: Corn, Wheat, Rice, 1961; 16mm film (Reel AV 857)
  - Harvest Workprint Reel #14: Potatoes, 1961; 16mm film (Reel AV 858)
  - Harvest - Workprint Reel #15: Columbia - Rural and Urban Slums, 1961; 16mm film (Reel AV 859)
  - La Herencia Del Ganadero, 1960; Sound, Color, 14 minutes.; 16mm film (Reel AV 131)
    Film about cattle farming in La Campana, Mexico. Randers driving cattle, usage of improved grains and grasses, experimental pesticides, identification of grass seeds, and proper water systems.
  - Horizontes: La Revolucion Verde (The Green Revolution), 1970s; Sound, Color, 14 minutes; 16mm film (Reel AV 134)
    The agricultural revolution in Mexico, Pakistan, India, Canada, Australia, and others. Shows Norman Borlaug receiving the Nobel Peace Prize for his related work, as well as field footage of Borlaug with farmers. Existing farming methods combined with modern techniques of fertilization, irrigation, crop rotation, and breeding methods.
  - International Rice Research Institute, 1963; Sound, Color, 11 minutes.; 16mm film (Reel AV 114)
    Film about new International Rice Research Institute headquarters in the Philippines, with dedication ceremonies footage showing guests John D. Rockefeller III, J.G. Harrar, and Robert Chandler. Discussion of the institute's concerns and efforts, including traditional rice farming, scientific methods, fertilization, laboratory work, and more. Extensive footage of the institute grounds, laboratories, and residential quarters.
  - International Rice Research Institute: Harvest of Energy, Sound, Color, 25 minutes.; 16mm film (Reel AV 144)
    Study of the biological, social, and environmental effects of rice in the human diet. Includes the production of new varieties, transplant techniques, testing of herbicides, water management, traditional methodologies, and other related criteria. Brief footage of press conference with John D. Rockefeller III and George Harrar of the Rockefeller Foundation and Henry T. Heald of the Ford Foundation. Filmed in cooperation with the government of the Philippines.
  - Let's Visit the College of Veterinary Medicine, Kasetsart University, Bangkok, Thailand, 1962; Sound, Black & white, 11 minutes. (Reel AV 118)
    Life at the veterinary school; laboratory, patients, operations on dogs and cattle, all with support from the Rockefeller Foundation. Features Dr. Luang Chai Asvaran, director of program, plus footage from university commencement attended by the King and Queen of Thailand.
    Other Finding Aids
    16mm film
  - A Man, His Ranch, and Merkeron (Una Ganadero, Su Rancho, U Zacate Merkeron), 1965; Sound, Black & white, 12 minutes; 16mm film (Reel AV 116)
    Film about agriculture in Mexico; Mexican dairy farmers at work, scientific approaches towards improving production, experimental lab work. Focus on fertilizing healthier grass in Merkeron.
  - Of Men and Ideas: An Interview with J.G. Harrar, 1963 April 4; Sound, Black & white, 60 minutes; 16mm film (Reel AV 149)
    Episode titled "Role of Foundations in Today's World". Host Richard Heffner, Channel WNDT manager, interviews J.G. Harrar, the president of the Rockefeller Foundation. Some questions: Is the phenomenon of giving strictly American? Do people within wealthy foundations play the role of God? What role do you think foundations will play in the future? What is an appropriate relationship between foundation and government policy?
  - Mexican Agricultural Program, c.1950; Sound, Color, 15 minutes; 16mm film (Reel AV 860)
    Related Materials
    The Mexican Agricultural Program (MAP) is also sometimes referred to as "Mexican Agriculture" or "Experiment to Revitalize Mexican Agriculture".
    "An experiment in International Cooperation between the government of Mexico and the Rockefeller Foundation": film introducing partnership between the Mexican government and the Rockefeller Foundation, and the focus of their work. Scenes of women making tortillas, Mexican corn varieties, cross-breeding plants, fight against plant disease, and experimentation with fertilizers.
  - One Tenth of Our Nation, 1940; Sound, Black & white, 25 minutes; 16mm film (Reel AV 31)
    Film produced in 1940 by the General Education Board which shows the limitations of education for the black population in the American South. History and current conditions of African Americans, from slavery and farming to special high school and college programs. Contrasting shots of impoverished villages and poor farms, with educated children learning job skills and modern training. Footage from George Washington Carver College.
  - "Open Mind" with Dr. John H. Knowles, Sound, Color, 28 minutes; 16mm film (Reel AV 872)
    Episode #0215 with Richard D. Heffner (Rutgers University) and Dr. John H. Knowles (RF).
  - Population Ecology, 1963; Sound, Color, 20 minutes; 16mm film (Reel AV 1705)
    Film made by Encyclopedia Britannica about the agricultural revolution and meeting the needs of a growing population. Uses lab tests with fruit flies and mice to discuss ecosystem restraints and natural population controls.
  - Programa de Adiestramiento Agro-Pecuario Popular, Sound, Black & white, 15 minutes; 16mm film (Reel AV 747)
    Training film about improving animal use on farms, presented by the Council of Rural Life.
  - Promises and Progress, 1967; Sound, Color, 11 minutes; 16mm film (Reel AV 130)
    Training film from the Mexican Ministry of Agriculture. Shows the interaction of RF officers with farmers and at stations. Experiments with potato production, disease-resistant seeds and cross-breeding, and preparation of soil.
  - Proytecto Puebla, CIMMYT, Sound, Color, 25 minutes; 16mm film (Reel AV 152)
    Educational film which describes the planting, fertilization, plowing, spraying, harvesting, and marketing of corn at the Puebla Project.
  - Rockefeller Foundation: Episode of The Today Show, 1964 April 27; Sound, Black & white, 30 minutes; 16mm film (Reel AV 43)
    J.G. Harrar and JDR 3rd being interviewed by James Daly and Maureen O'Sullivan. Part of publicity for the RF 50th anniversary and the publication of "Toward the Well-being of Mankind". Questions about JDR 3rd's personal giving as well as family legacy of philanthropy.
  - The Sardinian Project, 1948; Sound, Black and white, 36 minutes; 16mm film (Reel AV 42)
    This is the first half of a film which shows the campaign "Ente Regionale per la Lotta Anti-Anofelica en Sardengna (Regional Organization for the Anti-Anopheles or ERLAAS)" in Sardinia. Footage of village life, rampant malaria and its treatment with DDT spray. Produced by the Shell Oil Company. (The second half of the film is "Adventure in Sardinia").
  - Speaking Freely: Foundations and Philanthropy, 1968; Sound, Black & white, 55 minutes; 16mm film (Reel AV 49)
    Film in two parts: J.G. Harrar, president of the RF, being interviewed by Edwin Newman on NBC. Questions: How do foundations give away money? How do you measure success? What is the RF position on giving the public correct information and avoiding propaganda?
  - Schistosomiasis: Campaign in the Caribbean, c.1970s; Sound, Color, 25 minutes; 16mm film (Reel AV 147)
    Filmed by Jack Wolfgang Beck in St. Lucia, introducing the disease, its symptoms and means of infection, and the methodologies being used to research and treat the population. Laboratory work, experiments with mice, pesticide usage, construction to avoid infected areas and to make clean water available, and a series of interviews and footage exploring the assimilation of health education, methods taught to the public, and so on.
  - Unhooking the Hookworm, c.1922; Silent, Black & white, 10 minutes; 16mm film (Reel AV 123)
    Field and lab footage from the RF campaign to eradicate hookworm in the American South, showing the symptoms, diagnosis and treatment of hookworm. Includes scenes of environments where the disease exists and methods of prevention. Also includes some graphic imagery of the male and female worms and their parasitic behavior in humans.
  - War on Mosquitoes, c.1940; Sound, Black and white, 15 minutes; 16mm film (Reel AV 112)
    Produced by the Brazilian Ministry of Education and Health, showing cooperative actions with the Rockefeller Foundation to combat malaria. Presents problem of mosquitoes in Brazil and the methods of control: filling in water holes, spraying pesticides, laboratory work, mapping sites.
    Poor printing. Debris in the film gate obstructs the image.
- Rockefeller Foundation Videos, 2
  Currently no arrangement has been given by an archivist.
  Types of records include: videorecordings.
  - See Who's Here, c.1960s; 2 inch videotape; Sound, Black and white, 29 minutes (Reel AV 10633)
    Dr. Jacob George Harrar of the Rockefeller Foundation speaks with Dr. David Lewis from Oregon State University. Harrar discusses the origins of the Rockefeller Foundation, its history, and its programs.
  - AIDS in Thailand (Flecken auf der Haut), 1999; VHS; Sound, Color, 25 minutes (Tape AV 11057)
    Contains interviews with health industry workers discussing HIV/AIDS. Footage of urban prostitution and rural Thailand communities.
  - Norman Borlaug: Person of the Week - ABC-TV, VHS; Sound, color, 5 minutes (Box 108, Tape AV 11737)
    Aired nationally: 6:30-7:00pm on ABC-World News Tonight. Profile of American agronomist Norman Borlaug, who led initiatives worldwide that contributed to the extensive increases in agricultural production termed the Green Revolution. Borlaug was awarded multiple honors for his work, including the Nobel Peace Prize, the Presidential Medal of Freedom and the Congressional Gold Medal.
- Rockefeller Foundation Audio, 3
  - Remarks by Dr. Alan Gregg - Part 1, 1954 November 1; Sound,; 1/4 inch audio tape (Box 1, Reel AV 15238)
    Remarks by Dr. Alan Gregg from reocord of panel discussion organized by the Boston Society of Biologists.
  - Remarks by Dr. Alan Gregg - Part 2, 1954 November 1; Sound,; 1/4 inch audio tape (Box 1, Reel AV 15239)
  - How Healthy Are Americans, 1960 October 21; Sound,; 1/4 inch audio tape (Box 1, Reel AV 15240)
    Dr. John Grant was one of the participants
  - Dr. Warren Weaver Oral History - Part 1 and 2, 1961 April 27 and 1961 June 1; Sound,; 1/4 inch audio tape (Box 1, Reel AV 15241)
    Part 2: Interviewed by Barbara Land at the Rockefeller Foundation, New York.
  - Community Service Forum, 1963 April 11; Sound,; 1/4 inch audio tape (Box 1, Reel AV 15242)
  - Organization Anniversary: LP Record - Side 1A, circa 1963-1964; Sound,; 1/4 inch audio tape (Box 1, Reel AV 15243)
  - Organization Anniversary: LP Record - Side 1B, circa 1963-1964; Sound,; 1/4 inch audio tape (Box 1, Reel AV 15244)
  - Organization Anniversary: LP Record - Side 2A, circa 1963-1964; Sound,; 1/4 inch audio tape (Box 1, Reel AV 15245)
  - Organization Anniversary: LP Record - Side 2A, circa 1963-1964; Sound,; 1/4 inch audio tape (Box 1, Reel AV 15246)
  - J. George Harrar's interview with Lee Graham - WNYC Radio, 1969 June 24; Sound,; 1/4 inch audio tape (Box 1, Reel AV 15247)
  - Alan Douglas - WKYC-TV, 1969 July 10; Sound,; 1/4 inch audio tape (Box 1, Reel AV 15248)
  - The Stock Market Observer: George Harrar, 1969 July 17; Sound,; 1/4 inch audio tape (Box 1, Reel AV 15249)
  - J George Harrar Interview by Martha Deane - Part 1, 1969 July 28; Sound,; 1/4 inch audio tape (Box 1, Reel AV 15250)
  - J George Harrar Interview by Martha Deane - Part 2, 1969 July 28; Sound,; 1/4 inch audio tape (Box 1, Reel AV 15251)
  - The Rockefeller Foundation Service in Honor of Dr. Will M. Myers, 1970 July 31; Sound,; 1/4 inch audio tape (Box 1, Reel AV 15252)
  - J.G. Harrar Interview for March 11, 1963 New York Times Magazine Article, 1969 February 9; Sound,; 1/4 inch audio tape (Box 1, Reel AV 15253)
    Interview by Greer Williams.
  - Daniel P. Moynihan; JHK Wednesday Morning Officers Meeting, 1973 January 31; Sound,; 1/4 inch audio tape (Box 1, Reel AV 15254)
  - Recorded - KWT Scarsdale High School Studies Faculty, 1973 February 2; Sound,; 1/4 inch audio tape (Box 1, Reel AV 15255)
  - Michael Oksenberg - Contemporary China, 1973 April 11; Sound,; 1/4 inch audio tape (Box 1, Reel AV 15256)
  - Conquest of Hunger, 1973 May 3; Sound,; 1/4 inch audio tape (Box 1, Reel AV 15257)
  - Continuing Education in the Humanities - Michael Novak Conference, 1973 May 9; Sound,; 1/4 inch audio tape (Box 1, Reel AV 15258)
  - Arts Recording Project Conum HK and Outside Guests, [1973] May 10; Sound,; 1/4 inch audio tape (Box 1, Reel AV 15259)
  - Robert Goheen - On foundations, 1973 April 25; Sound,; 1/4 inch audio tape (Box 1, Reel AV 15260)
  - James MacGregor Burns, 1973 May 18; Sound,; 1/4 inch audio tape (Box 1, Reel AV 15261)
  - Vincent P. Dole -Seminar Wednesday Morning Meeting Group: Drug Abuse, 1973 May 16; Sound,; 1/4 inch audio tape (Box 1, Reel AV 15262)
  - Humanities - Michael Novak: The Pluralistic Sensibilities in the Humanities, 1973 May 11; Sound,; 1/4 inch audio tape (Box 1, Reel AV 15263)
  - JHK Meeting with Officers; J.G. Harrar Speaks on his China Tour., 1973 July 3; Sound,; 1/4 inch audio tape (Box 1, Reel AV 15264)
  - Fr. Andrew Greeley and Michael Novak Speak to JHK and Rockefeller Foundation Officers, 1972 November 22; Sound,; 1/4 inch audio tape (Box 1, Reel AV 15265)
  - Meeting of Rockefeller Foundation Staff Officers and Mayor Kevin White; Speaking on Urban Problem, 1973 July 18; Sound,; 1/4 inch audio tape (Box 1, Reel AV 15266)
  - Michael Novak - Seminar on Humanities, 1973 July 25; Sound,; 1/4 inch audio tape (Box 1, Reel AV 15267)
    JHK attended
  - Hudson Basin Project RWR and Committee, 1973 September 11; Sound,; 1/4 inch audio tape (Box 1, Reel AV 15268)
    Morning session not recorded - Afternoon session on Side 1
  - Aquaculture - J.A.P., 1973 October 2; Sound,; 1/4 inch audio tape (Box 1, Reel AV 15269)
    Speakers: David Wallace, Burr Steinback, Alexander Spoehr, Barry Fisher and Harold Goodwin
  - Otto Feinstein: Neighborhoods and Cities, 1973 September 26; Sound,; 1/4 inch audio tape (Box 1, Reel AV 15270)
    Wednesday Morning Seminars with Otto Feinstein from Division of Science of Society, Wayne State University.
  - James Grant From Oversees Development Council, 1973 October 17; Sound,; 1/4 inch audio tape (Box 1, Reel AV 15271)
    Wednesday Morning Seminar
  - Plant Resistance to Insect Attacks, 1973 October 30; Sound,; 1/4 inch audio tape (Box 1, Reel AV 15272)
  - Joseph Papp: Contemporary Values in America, 1973 October 31; Sound,; 1/4 inch audio tape (Box 1, Reel AV 15273)
  - Journalism and the Humanities, 1973 November 12; Sound,; 1/4 inch audio tape (Box 1, Reel AV 15274)
  - JHK Wednesday Morning Meeting: Peter Berger - Professor Of Sociology, Rutgers University, 1969 December; Sound,; 1/4 inch audio tape (Box 2, Reel AV 15304)
  - Earl O. Heady Spoke at Wednesday Morning Meeting, 1974 January 9; Sound,; 1/4 inch audio tape (Box 2, Reel AV 15305)
  - Elmore Jackson Conference - All Day (Weather and Climate Change), 1974 January 24; Sound,; 1/4 inch audio tape (Box 2, Reel AV 15306)
  - Conference on Weather and Climate Change, Food Production and Inter-State Conflict, 1974 January 24 and 1974 January 25; Sound,; 1/4 inch audio tape (Box 2, Reel AV 15307)
  - Wednesday Morning Meeting: JHK, Topic: Program Related Investments, Ford Foundation Representative, Arthur Trottenburg, Eamon Kelly, Paul Feinberg, and James Jordan, 1974 February 15; Sound,; 1/4 inch audio tape (Box 2, Reel AV 15308)
  - Dr. Davidson RKD - EFD Meeting, 1973 November 19; Sound,; 1/4 inch audio tape (Box 2, Reel AV 15309)
    9am-12:30pm
  - Dr. Davidson's (Afternoon) - RKD - EFD Meeting, Part I, 1973 November 19; Sound,; 1/4 inch audio tape (Box 2, Reel AV 15310)
    1pm